University of Connecticut
© 2006 University of Connecticut
University of Connecticut, University Libraries Director's Records [John P. MacDonald, 1963-1988].
undated, 1950s-1980s
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Center.
MacDonald, John P.
34 linear feet
MSS19980248
John P. MacDonald was the Director of the University of Connecticut Libraries from 1963 through 1986. The collection contains correspondence, reports, studies and information on the Libraries' and associated programs, as well as materials pertaining to MacDonald's interests in birds.
Biography
John P. McDonald ( 1922-1993 ) graduated from the University of Virginia in 1946 after serving four years in the U. S. Navy during World War II. He earned a Masters of Library Science from Drexel University in 1951 and in 1975 received the Drexel Library School Alumni Association's Outstanding Alumnus Award. He worked at the University of Pennsylvania Library for a short time before moving to the Washington University Library in St. Louis where he became an associate director. Early in the administration of President Homer D. Babbidge, Jr., he was appointed University Librarian at UConn (1963). He helped design and oversaw the planning of the new university library, which was subsequently named after President Babbidge in the late 1970s. He was a consultant on library buildings and management for many libraries. Active in state, regional, national, and international library associations and organizations, MacDonald served as President of the Association of Research Libraries (ARL) in 1971/1972; from 1974 to 1976, while on leave from UConn, he was Executive Director of ARL. Upon his return to UConn, he was named Director of University Libraries and held that position until becoming Director of Library Development about a year before his retirement in 1988. By the time he retired the library's collections had grown from about 450,000 volumes to more than 2,500,000 volumes. During his tenure the library took initial steps towards library automation, played an active role in state, regional, and national library network and resource sharing developments, and built strong archival and special collections. The UConn Alumni Association honored him with its Leadership Award in 1986.
MacDonald was an avid bird watcher, conservationist, and naturalist. For many years, he served on the board of Joshua's Tract Conservation and Historic Trust, and was secretary of the Friends of Trail Wood in Hampton, connecticut. His close relationship with Edwin and Nellie Teale was instrumental in the eventual addition of Teale's papers to Special Collections. He was also an active member of the National and Connecticut Audubon Societies, the Connecticut Ornithological Society, and the Natchaug Ornithological Society. His collection of more than 1,000 bird books, which he donated to Special Collections, is housed in the John P. McDonald Reading Room in the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Scope and Content
The collection include materials relating not only to MacDonald's work in the UConn Library but in many other aspects of his professional career and his interest in natural history.
Arrangement
Inventory ( undated, ). The collection has not been organized into Series.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students, etc.]. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Separated Material
The MacDonald collection of monographs pertaining to birds has been cataloged and titles may be found by searching the Libraries' online catalog, Homer.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
MacDonald, John P.
Subjects:
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.; Minutes.; Manuscripts.; Photocopies.; Notes.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was transferred by the Administrative office of the University Libraries' in 1998.
Detailed Description
- Inventory, undated, 1950s-1980s
  - (Box 1)
    - Acorn Club, undated
    - Joshua's Trust, undated
    - Connecticut Ornithological Association, undated
    - Natchaug Ornithological Association, undated
    - Other groups, undated
  - (Box 2)
    - Consultations, undated
    - Clubs, undated
    - Regional library associations and organizations, undated
    - Library materials, undated
  - (Box 3)
    - Consultations, undated
  - (Box 4)
    - Lecture notes for teaching, late 1950s/early 1960s
    - St. Louis material, undated
  - (Box 5)
    - Job offers, undated
    - Conferences, undated
    - Personal material, undated
  - (Box 6)
    - University and Library materials, late 1970s/early 1980s
  - (Box 7)
    - University and Library materials, 1977-1978
  - (Box 8)
    - Council on Library Resources PETREL (Professional Education and Training of Research Librarians) Project, undated
  - (Box 9)
    - University and Library materials, undated
  - (Box 10)
    - University and Library materials, undated
    - Other state materials, undated
  - (Box 11)
    - University and Library materials, undated
    - Personal papers (partly organized), undated
  - (Box 12)
    - University and Library materials, late 1970s
  - (Box 13)
    - Construction of Babbidge Library, undated
  - (Box 14)
    - University and Library materials, undated
  - (Box 15)
    - Council on Library Resources PETREL project, undated
  - (Box 16)
    - University and Library materials, 1979-1980
  - (Box 17)
    - University and Library materials, 1976-1977
  - (Box 18)
    - University and Library materials, circa 1978
  - (Box 19)
    - American Library Association (ALA) and related materials, 1965-1966
  - (Box 20)
    - Presentations, undated
    - Groups, undated
    - Personal materials including speeches/writings, undated
  - (Box 21)
    - University and Library materials, late 1970s/early 1980s
  - (Box 22)
    - University and Library materials, undated
    - Personal papers, undated
  - (Box 23)
    - University and Library materials (including development activities), 1980s